Aleksander Emelyanov

Profile

Summary

Software engineer with 12+ years of experience. Open source maintainer and contributor. In my spare time, I launched a car-sharing startup in St. Petersburg, while maintaining high productivity at my main job. Top 1 student in first semester of Mail.ru Big Data Academy from 2020 recruitment.

Roles

- Software Engineer
- Backend Developer

Key technologies:

- Languages: Ruby, Python, Go, C++
- Storages and queues: PostgreSQL, Redis, RabbitMQ, S3
- Deploy and automation: Linux, Docker, Kubernetes, Terraform, Vault, AWS
- · Frontend: HTML, CSS, JavaScript, jQuery, React.js
- VCS: Git
- Basic ML: feature engineering, simple models, gradient boosting models

Job history

Software Engineer at Deep Learn Inc

Period	Jan 2017 - Present
Location	Remote
Stack	Ruby, Ruby on Rails, RSpec, Sidekiq, ActiveAdmin, PostgreSQL, Python, Celery, Terraform, Heroku, AWS, Kubernetes, Git
Job	Designed and developed backend, API and management UI for cluster management system to run our AutoML payload + developed a couple of related microservices. Added support of RabbitMQ to open source Keda scaler to implement autoscaling in our Kubernetes clusters. Implemented integration test which detected tens of broken commits. Optimized unit tests and made them 2x faster. Completely fixed false negatives in UI tests by rewriting them from Capybara to Cypress. Rewrited 10k CLOC Django project to Rails in 10 days and increased test coverage from 80% to 95%.

Lead Software Engineer at Digital Car

Period	Oct 2016 - Jan 2020	
Location	Location Saint Petersburg	
Stack	Ruby, Ruby on Rails, RSpec, Sidekiq, ActiveAdmin, PostgreSQL, EventMachine, DigitalOcean, Ansible, Capistrano, Git	
Job	Designed, developed and supported a carsharing solution for colesa.com - carsharing in Saint Petersburg. One-man project in a free-time, MVP serving real cars and customers was created in 2 monthes, whole system worked in production 3 years with tens of cars and hundreeds of customers. Solution includes: • Car Server - event-machine based TCP server which collects telemetry and sends control commands to car-trackers	
	 Web Server - handles all business logic and provides APIs for client applications (Web and mobile apps) 	
	Admin Web UI - CRM for carsharing employees	

Software Engineer at SPB TV

Period	Sep 2014 - Jan 2017
Location	Saint Petersburg
Stack	Ruby, Ruby on Rails, RSpec, Sidekiq, ActiveAdmin, PostgreSQL, Docker, Ansible, Git
Job	Participated in design and developing of backend, API, and management UI for TV streaming platform (OTT middleware). Supported system in production, optimised code and DB design to work under load. Halved the average API response time.

Software Developer at VIAcode

Period	Jul 2012 - Sep 2014
Location	Saint Petersburg
Stack	C#, ASP.Net MVC, MS SQL, MS System Center, Ruby, JavaScript, Ember.js, TFS
Job	Participated in developing of MS SCOM management packs. Extend SCOM with a bunch of cool widgets which were highly appreciated by the Microsoft employees.

Software Developer at LLC "Technologii Avtomatizatsii"

Period	Jul 2009 - Jul 2012
Location	Saint Petersburg
Stack	C#, C++/CLI, MS SQL, SVN
Job	Designed, developed, and supported an environmental monitoring system. Wrote drivers for tens of different hardware devices for data acquisition. Lead the small team.

Software Developer at Research Institute of Electronic production equipment and communication systems

Period	Jul 2008 - Jun 2009
Location	Tomsk
Stack	Delphi, C++, SVN
Job	Developed tools for internal usage and monitoring systems for an industrial production.

Education

Period	2003 - 2008
Location	Tomsk State University of Control Systems and Radioelectronics
Faculty	Radio Design at Department of Radio Electronic Technologies and Environmental Monitoring
Specialization	Design and Technology of Radio Electronic Tools
Degree work	Computer simulation system for microstrip lines for integrated microwave devices.

Open source

Author and maintainer of

- https://github.com/holyketzer/activeadmin-ajax_filter
- https://github.com/holyketzer/activeadmin-async_panel

Most popular projects I contributed to

- https://github.com/rails/rails
- https://github.com/kedacore/keda
- https://github.com/fission/fission

Hobbies

- Jogging & hiking
- DIY
- Music & books

Links

- https://github.com/holyketzer
- https://www.linkedin.com/in/aemelyanov86/
- https://www.kaggle.com/holyketzer